{"tossups": [{"question": "As a young boy, this noble\u2019s predilection for surrounding himself with peasants led to him being known as \u201cThe Great Fool of Owari.\u201d This man innovated the use of the concentrated volley to defeat the Takeda Clan at the Battle of Nagashino. The Honno-ji incident led to this daimyo\u2019s death and the killing of clan leader Akechi Mitsuhide at the hand of this man\u2019s disciple, Toyotomi Hideyoshi. For the point, name this ally of Tokugawa Ieyasu, known as the \u201cGreat Unifier\u201d of Japan.", "answer": "Oda Nobunaga (accept either or both)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Many historians have praised this 2012 film for its accuracy, including the title character\u2019s high pitched voice and talent for storytelling. Inspired by Doris Kearns Goodwin\u2019s Team of Rivals, this movie centers on the debate and negotiation surrounding the passage of the 13th Amendment. For the point, name this Steven Spielberg film featuring Tommy Lee Jones as Thaddeus Stevens and an Academy Award-winning performance by Daniel Day-Lewis as the 16th U.S. president.", "answer": "Lincoln", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A pioneer in the research of these objects donated his skull to charity so that his brain size could be compared to that of his rival\u2019s. Edward Drinker Cope and Othniel Charles Marsh feuded over these objects in a \u201cwar\u201d in the late 1800\u2019s. Regions called Lagerst \u0308atten [LAH-ger-shtet-en] with minimal bacterial activity contain high-quality objects of this type, and the Burgess Shale contains objects of this type from the Cambrian period. For the point, what are these preserved remains of organisms studied by paleontologists?", "answer": "Fossils (prompt on \u201cbones\u201d)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Misc Science"}, {}, {"question": "While serving an empire named for this city, Alexios Strategopoulos besieged  Constantinople. This city names a Byzantine rump state ruled by Michael VIII Palaiologos. A church council in this city called by Irene [ay-REH-nee] of Athens supported the veneration of images, ending the First Iconoclasm. An earlier council in this city created a document beginning \u201cWe believe in one God,\u201d its namesake \u201ccreed.\u201d For the point, name this Turkish city that hosted the first Christian church council in 325.", "answer": "Nicea (accept with either soft C or hard C pronunciation)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man, whose reforms began on \u201cYear Zero,\u201d assisted the Lon Nol government in their overthrow of King Norodom Sihanouk. This man\u2019s regime committed genocide against the intelligentsia and political dissidents in the \u201cKilling Fields.\u201d A 1979 Vietnamese invasion toppled this man\u2019s government in favor of the Soviet-aligned People\u2019s Republic of Kampuchea. For the point, name this Communist dictator of Cambodia, the head of the Khmer Rouge.", "answer": "Pol Pot (accept Saloth Sar; in either case, accept either or both names)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This philosopher was reportedly so strict about his schedule that neighbors would set their clocks based on his daily walks. Klemens von Metternich was inspired by this philosopher\u2019s proposal for \u201cperpetual peace.\u201d This German\u2019s argument that one should act as if their action will become universal law is contained in the Groundwork of the Metaphysics of Morals. For the point, name this philosopher who proposed the \u201ccategorical imperative\u201d and wrote a Critique of Pure Reason", "answer": "Immanuel <b>Kant </b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "This \u201cagreement\u201d was described as \u201cDraconian\u201d and \u201cvery unfair\u201d in a speech given at the White House Rose Garden. This agreement fulfilled some of the framework adopted by the Durban Platform at a multi-national conference in 2011. This 2015 agreement built on the Copenhagen Accords and the Montreal Protocol. For the point, name this \u201cClimate Accord\u201d negotiated in France that Donald Trump intends to pull the US out of in November, 2020.", "answer": "Paris Agreement (accept Paris Climate Accord(s))", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Eitri forged a gold artifact for this god that multiplied itself during a contest with the Sons of Ivaldi. This god used the name Bolverk when he took the Mead of Poetry from Baugi. This god\u2019s son Vidar will avenge him at Ragnarok by killing the wolf Fenrir. At the well of Mimir, this god gave up an eye to gain wisdom, and he learned the runes by starving himself on a branch of Yggdrasil. For the point, name this Norse \u201call-father\u201d who rules Valhalla.", "answer": "Odin (accept Wotan)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s wife, Polina Zhemchuzhina [zhem-SHOO-zhee-na], the onetime Soviet Minister of Fisheries, was sent into \u201cinternal exile\u201d largely due to her Jewish faith. A \u201ctroika\u201d of Malenkov, Beria, and this minister took over immediately after the death of Joseph Stalin. With Ribbentrop, this man names a non-aggression pact between Nazi Germany and the Soviet Union. For the point, name this Soviet minister that names a \u201ccocktail,\u201d first used by Finns as an incendiary weapon.", "answer": "Vyacheslav <b>Molotov </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In a battle during this conflict, Peter Bartholomew\u2019s \u201cdiscovery\u201d of the Holy Lance led to his routing of forces under Emir Kerbogha [care-BOW-ah]. In the prelude to this war, Peter the Hermit led peasants and noblemen alike in pogroms of Jews in Central Europe. This conflict began when Alexios I Komnenos called for western Christians to turn back the invading Seljuk Turks. For the point, name this Christian crusade called by Urban II in 1095.", "answer": "First <b>Crusade </b>(accept Prince\u2019s Crusade, prompt on People\u2019s Crusade)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One segment of this work was adapted by Dave Malloy into an electro-pop opera, starring Philippa Soo as Natasha. That musical is based on just seventy pages of this book, focusing on Natasha\u2019s relationships with Anatole and Pierre while her betrothed, Andrey, is fighting against Napoleon. Natasha, Pierre, and the Great Comet of 1812 is based on, for the point, what famously long Tolstoy novel about the French invasion of Russia?", "answer": "War and Peace (accept Voyna i mir)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "Outside of the River Rouge Plant, agents from this company were photographed beating Walter Reuther during the Battle of the Overpass. The Whiz Kids, which included Robert McNamara, helped reform this company\u2019s operations. This company\u2019s founder stated that one of its products was available \u201cin any color the customer wants, so long as it is black.\u201d This company introduced the 40-hour work week and the assembly line. For the point, name this Dearborn, Michigan-based auto company whose namesake founder created the Model T.", "answer": "<b>Ford</b> Motor Company", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this former nation, the arrest of the psychedelic band PPU led to dissidents criticizing the government in the manifesto \u201cCharter 77.\u201d Former child actress Shirley Temple served as ambassador to this former nation, in part due to her presence during the Soviet overthrow of the Alexander Dubcek [DOOB-chek] government. This European nation experienced the Velvet Divorce, splitting it into two distinct ethno-states. For the point, name this former Eastern European country with the cities of Bratislava and Prague.", "answer": "Czechoslovakia (do not accept Czechia, Czech Republic, or Slovakia)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this ongoing war, the Transitional Federal Government, with help from AMISOM forces, recaptured a capital in 2011 from the terrorist cell Al-Shabaab. This war began in the late 1980s due to events such as the Isaaq genocide under the dictatorship of Siad Barre. This civil war has increased general piracy in the Red Sea region, and it led to creation five autonomous regions including Puntland. For the point, name this civil war that included the fall of Mogadishu.", "answer": "Somali Civil War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Dressmaker Elizabeth Keckley\u2019s 1868 memoir, Behind the Scenes, ended her friendship with this woman. This woman lived to see her son Robert become U.S. Secretary of War, but she outlived her other three children. Most of this woman\u2019s Lexington, Kentucky family supported the Confederacy, opposing her husband\u2019s government. For the point, name this First Lady, who was seated next to her husband when he was assassinated at Ford\u2019s Theatre.", "answer": "<b>Mary </b>Todd <b>Lincoln </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Both of this man\u2019s grandfathers were arrested during the Great Purge of 1937, leading to this man\u2019s support of the anti-Stalinist reforms of Nikita Kruschev while serving as First Secretary in Stavropol. Having succeeded Konstantin Chernenko in his highest position, this man remained committed to socialism while promoting glasnost and perestroika. For the point, name this man, Time\u2019s Man of the Decade for the 1980s, who in 1990 was elected President of the Soviet Union.", "answer": "Mikhail <b>Gorbachev </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This political entity may have actually been the legendary Kwedech who were expelled from the last land, Gespedeg, and out of the St. Lawrence River region by the Mi\u2019kmaq. This entity fought in low stakes, minimal bloodshed wars known as Mourning Wars against groups like the Petun and Susquehannock. This confederacy fought the Beaver Wars against both the French and the Huron. For the point, name this confederacy of Five Nations including the Onondaga, Oneida, Cayuga, Seneca, and Mohawk.", "answer": "<b>Iroquois</b> Confederacy (accept Iroquois League, accept Haudenosaunee, accept Five Nations until it is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This place was mentioned in the Beatles song \u201cA Day in the Life,\u201d and Alfred Hitchcock filmed the climax of The Man Who Knew Too Much in this place. The first concert held in this venue was Arthur Sullivan\u2019s On Shore and Sea on May 1, 1871. The 25th anniversary performance of The Phantom of the Opera was filmed in, for the point, what 5,000 seat London concert hall, built by Queen Victoria in memory of her husband?", "answer": "Royal <b>Albert Hall </b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {"question": "This country\u2019s MR8 guerilla group kidnapped U.S. ambassador Charles Elbrick. This country\u2019s leader Juscelino Kubitschek built its new capital farther inland as part of his interior development plan. This country\u2019s president Getu \u0301lio Vargas established its state-owned oil company Petrobras, which was tied to this country\u2019s president Dilma Rousseff in a 2015 scandal. For the point, name this largest and only Portuguese-speaking country in South America.", "answer": "Federative Republic of <b>Brazil </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During this war, George Anson was deployed to the Pacific to disrupt the Acapulco to Manila trade route. The American theater of this war began when Spanish captain Juan de Le \u0301on Fandin \u0303o cut off Robert Jenkins\u2019s ear as a penalty for smuggling. The ceding of Silesia and the weakening of the Dutch Republic were provisions of this war\u2019s Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle. For the point, name this war that initially concerned the right of a woman, in this case Maria Theresa, to inherit the Habsburg throne.", "answer": "War of the Austrian Succession", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Diplomat Spruille [sprool] Braden tried to discredit this leader\u2019s campaign with the \u201cBlue Book.\u201d Edelmiro Farrell helped this politician create a Department of Labour. This leader helped Ludwig and Rodolfo Freude organize \u201cratlines\u201d through his country. This leader was ousted in a coup after the Plaza del Mayo was bombed in 1953. This leader\u2019s supporters were known as the \u201cdescamisados.\u201d For the point, name this president of Argentina and husband of Evita.", "answer": "Juan <b>Peron </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This structure attracted up to a million people to a celebration of its 50th anniversary in 1987 which caused its main span to flatten. A 1962 commission advised against using BART trains on this structure which would have provided a public transit option to Marin County. Proximity to the San Andreas Fault puts this structure at risk, but suicide jumps have been the greatest danger, leading to a $200 million safety net project. For the point, name this bridge spanning the strait at the mouth of San Francisco Bay.", "answer": "Golden Gate Bridge", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This man lost his brother in Operation Yonatan, an attempt to save hostages at Entebbe Airport. This man earned his Master\u2019s Degree from MIT, taking a break in 1973 to fight in the Yom Kippur War. This prime minister, who previously fought in the Six Days War as a member of Israeli special forces, funded the mass emigration of Ethiopian Jews to his nation in 2015. For the point, name this longest serving Prime Minister of Israel.", "answer": "Benjamin \u201cBibi\u201d <b>Netanyahu </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The Venerable Bede wrote of a king of this region named Cadwallon, who attempted to check Edwin of Diera\u2019s attempts to conquer the Mevanian Isles. Offa the Great built a namesake dyke that delineated the borders of Mercia and this region. The jailing of Eleanor de Monfort led to Edward Longshanks\u2019s 13th century conquest of this country including the kingdom of Gwynedd. For the point, name this constituent country in the U.K. with the cities of Swansea and Cardiff.", "answer": "Wales", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "An expedition along this river\u2019s drainage basin led by Ca\u02c6ndido Rondon and Teddy Roosevelt nearly killed Roosevelt from an infected leg. Along a tributary of this river, a motor company founded the ill-fated settlement of Fordlandia to streamline rubber production for car tires. Francis de Orellana gave this river its myth-inspired name after he fought multiple skirmishes with female dominated tribes. For the point, name this largest river by volume discharge in the world, located in South America.", "answer": "<b>Amazon</b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This island was the site of the founding of the world\u2019s first environmental political party and the location of the Black War in the 1820s and \u201830s. This island was home to the thylacine, also known as this island\u2019s \u201ctiger\u201d until its extinction in 1936. Port Arthur, a former prison colony on this island, was the home of many transported convicts in the 19th century near the city of Hobart. Formerly known as Van Diemen\u2019s Land, for the point, name this island now named for a Dutch navigator, counted as one of the states of Australia.", "answer": "Tasmania (prompt on \u201cTAS\u201d or \u201cTassie\u201d)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "One member of this movement used a tricycle to protest after being crippled by polio. The daughter of the last Sikh Maharaja was one of over 300 people violently expelled from the House of Commons on Black Friday during this movement. Rosa May Billinghurst and Sophia Duleep Singh joined Emmaline Pankhurst\u2019s Women\u2019s Social and Political Union during, for the point, what movement to expand the right to vote in England?", "answer": "British <b>women\u2019s suffrage movement</b> (accept Women\u2019s right to vote before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}